<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6347 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6347.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6066 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6066.xml">
<!-- <!ENTITY RFC7252 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7252.xml"> --> 
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dice-profile SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dice-profile.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.barrett-mobile-dtls SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.barrett-mobile-dtls.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-tls-tls13 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-tls-tls13.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-fossati-tls-iot-optimizations" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DTLS/TLS Optimizations for IoT">TLS/DTLS Optimizations for Internet of Things Deployments</title>
    <author fullname="Thomas Fossati" initials="T.F." surname="Fossati">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Cambridge</city>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <email>thomas.fossati@nokia.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Hannes Tschofenig" initials="H.T." surname="Tschofenig">
      <organization>ARM</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Cambridge</city>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <email>hannes.tschofenig@arm.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Nikos Mavrogiannopoulos" initials="N.M." surname="Mavrogiannopoulos">
      <organization>Red Hat</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Brno</city>
          <country>Czech Republic</country>
        </postal>
        <email>nmav@redhat.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <keyword>DTLS, TLS, Internet of Things, IoT, TLS extensions</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Internet protocols work well in a variety of environments, including Internet of Things (IoT) deployments. While there are some optimization possibilities to reduce code size, bandwidth utilization, and to improve battery lifetime in general most Internet protocols are also applicable to constrained environments. TLS and DTLS are two such security protocols that can be used by many IoT devices since DTLS/TLS provide lot of flexiblity in terms credential choice, ciphersuite usage, etc. The DICE working group has developed a specification that profiles the use of TLS and DTLS for IoT environments, without changing the TLS/DTLS specifications.</t>

<t>This memo goes a step further and proposes changes to the DTLS/TLS protocol to introduce further optimizations. Since the ongoing work on TLS/DTLS 1.3 already offers several improvements (compared to previous versions) this document focuses on the use of version 1.3 and suggests further optimizations.</t>

    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
 <t>Internet protocols work well in a variety of environments, including Internet of Things (IoT) deployments. While there are some optimization possibilities to reduce code size, bandwidth utilization, and to improve battery lifetime in general most Internet protocols are also applicable to constrained environments. TLS and DTLS are two such security protocols that can be used by many IoT devices since DTLS/TLS provide lot of flexiblity in terms credential choice, ciphersuite usage, etc. The DICE working group has developed a specification that profiles the use of TLS and DTLS for IoT environments, without changing the TLS/DTLS specifications.</t>

<t>This memo goes a step further and proposes changes to the DTLS/TLS protocol to introduce further optimizations. Since the ongoing work on TLS/DTLS 1.3 <xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-tls13"/> already offers several improvements (compared to previous versions) this document focuses on the use of version 1.3 and suggests further optimizations.</t>

<t>This document discusses four extensions, namely 
<list style="hanging">

<t hangText="Selective Fragment Retransmission:"> This extension improves retransmissions of lost handshake packets.</t>
<t hangText="Transport Agnostic Security Associations:"> Changes to a connection (such as an IP address change) requires a new handshake. This extension introduces a transport independent identifier.</t> 
<t hangText="Reducing the DTLS Record Layer Header Overhead:"> This extension changes the record layer format to reduce the overhead.</t>
<t hangText="Reducing Buffers:"> This extension allows a DTLS/TLS server running on a constrained node to indicate its buffer size.</t>
</list> 
</t> 

</section> 


      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>

    <?rfc needLines="8" ?>
    <section title="Selective Fragment Retransmission" anchor="sec:snack">
      <section title="Problem Statement">
        <t>The unit of retransmission used by the DTLS handshake is a whole flight (see Section 4.2.4 of <xref target="RFC6347" />. If the underlying media is inherently lossy, or shows high latency variance that might fire spurious retransmission, a single fragment that gets lost or is excessively delayed will force the whole flight to be retransmitted .</t>
        <t>This is further exacerbated when the effective MTU is very low and therefore handshake messages have higher probability to be fragmented.  For example, IEEE 802.15.4 networks have a 128-byte MTU size. In such an environment a very "ordinary" TLS_ECDHE_RSA_WITH_AES_256_CBC_SHA negotiation can take up to 30 individual fragments, 2/3 of which are sent in flight 4.  The loss of a single fragment in flight 4 implies a retransmission that is 20x the magnitude of the original loss.</t>
        <t>The retransmission timer settings suggested in Section 11 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-dice-profile"/> offer mitigation for the spurious retransmit issue and, in general, help with congestion. However, they do not solve the retransmission of the entire flight. </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Proposal">
        <t>A potential solution is to add a NACK-based retransmission scheme to the DTLS handshake and the granularity of retransmission would be a message fragment.  We note that each fragment in a DTLS handshake is effectively associated to a unique identifier defined by the tuple Handshake.{message_seq,fragment_offset,fragment_length} that can be used in the NACK report to identify the exact geometry of the missing data in the current flight, together with the right-most received byte.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Transport Agnostic Security Associations" anchor="sec:ta-sa">
      <section title="Problem Statement">
        <t>In DTLS, the security context demultiplexing is done via the 5-tuple. This implies that the associated DTLS context needs to be re-negotiated from scratch whenever the IP address changes. For example, when moving the network attachment from WLAN to a cellular connection, or when the IP address of the IoT devices changes during a sleep cyle. A NAT device may also modify the source UDP port after some a longer idle period.</t>
        <t>On such situations, there is not enough information in the DTLS record header for a DTLS server, which handles multiple clients, to associate the changed address to an existing client without relying on a re-handshake.</t>
        <t>In Low Power and Lossy Networks (LLNs), or in situations where one of the two parties is a constrained device, the DTLS handshake tends to be expensive and fragile (see Section 11 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-dice-profile"/>).</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Proposal">
        <t>A potential solution is to add the ability to negotiate, at handshake time, a transport independent identifier that is unique per security association. We call this identifier the 'Connection ID (CID)' in <xref target="fig:scid"/>. It allows to decouple the DTLS session from the underlying transport protocol allowing the same DTLS security association to be migrated.</t>
        <figure title="Transparent Handover of DTLS Session" anchor="fig:scid">
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
                                     00
                                     /\
                                     :
 IP                    UDP           : DTLS Record Header
 +-----+-----+-------+ +-----+-----+ : +---------+-------+------
 | src | dst | proto | | src | dst | : | Seq#i   |  CID  | ...
 +-----+-----+-------+ +-----+-----+ : +---------+-------+------
 `----------------+----------------' :              ^
                   `................ : .............'
  <Handover event>                   :
                   GSM-SMS           : DTLS Record Header
                   +-------+-------+ : +---------+-------+-----
                   | tp-oa | tp-da | : | Seq#i+1 |  CID  | ...
                   +-------+-------+ : +---------+-------+-----
                                     :
                                     \/
                                     00
            ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>That approach modifies the DTLS record layer header to the format described in <xref target="fig:record-format"/>.</t>
                <figure title="Modified DTLS Record Format" anchor="fig:record-format">
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
      struct {
           ContentType type;
           ProtocolVersion version;
           uint16 epoch;
           uint48 sequence_number;
           uint32 connection_id;                          // New field
           uint16 length;
           opaque fragment[DTLSPlaintext.length];
      } DTLSPlaintext;
            ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>A similar approach to support transparent handover of a DTLS session has been described in <xref target="I-D.barrett-mobile-dtls"/> and <xref target="Seggelmann"/>.</t>
        <t>The privacy issue associated with the use of a long-term identifier must be taken into consideration.  For example, client and server could use a hash chain <xref target="Lamport"/> derived from the shared secret and pick the next unused id on handover.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Reducing the DTLS Record Layer Header Overhead" anchor="sec:diet">
      <section title="Problem Statement">
        <t>The DTLS record layer header adds 13 bytes of overhead, as described in Appendix B of <xref target="I-D.ietf-dice-profile"/>. While some of the information carried in the header is unavoidable there are other parameters that are redundant and included for backwards compatibility reasons. This burden becomes quite substantial in networks with small frame sizes (e.g., low power wide area networks).</t>
        <t>Overhead that is not strictly needed could be removed to allow applications to transmit more data in a single packet or to make space for other DTLS features, such as the proposal described in <xref target="sec:ta-sa"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Proposal">
        <t>It is possible to at least remove the following parameters in the header: 
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Protocol Version (2 bytes)</t>
            <t>The sequence number
      component of the nonce_explicit field at the AES-CCM layer is an
      exact copy of the sequence number in the record layer header
      field. This leads to a duplication of 8-bytes per record.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Reducing Buffers" anchor="sec:server-mfl">
      <section title="Problem Statement">
        <t>The Maximum Fragment Length extension <xref target="RFC6066"/> allows a client with limited buffer space to specify a different (smaller) maximum size for fragments that the server is allowed to send.  The mechanism is not symmetrical: a server cannot state their buffer size.  The assumption made in <xref target="RFC6066"/> is that the server is never going to be a constrained device, and therefore does not need such a capability. While this may be true for many IoT deployments where the TLS client is implemented in an IoT device that connects to a server on the Internet that does not have memory limitations, such as a server in the cloud. However, with the desire to also deploy CoAPS and HTTPS-based servers in IoT devices that respond to requests a constrained node may also need to run a DTLS/TLS server. In such a  scenario, allowing a constrained server to advertise its Maximum Fragment Length helps to lower memory requirements.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Proposal">
        <t>The semantics of the max_fragment_length extension could be modified to allow the server as well as the client to express their buffer sizes. </t>
      </section>
    </section>
<!-- 
    <section title="0-RTT Client Authentication" anchor="sec:0rtt-cliauth">
      <section title="Problem Statement">
        <t>The ability to do 0-RTT mutual authentication would provide a very compelling reason for moving IoT security from (D)TLS 1.2 to 1.3, since IoT devices typically need a mutually authenticated secure channel.  Unfortunately, based on feedback from the TRON workshop, the TLS working group decided to remove Client Authentication from 0-RTT starting with version -13 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-tls13"/>.  In fact, as described in <xref target="Bhargavan"/>, the mechanism offers less-than-ideal security properties: the authentication is tied to the client's (EC)DH share which effectively becomes a long-term DH certificate.  As a consequence, an impersonation attack arises when the client's ephemeral key is compromised.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Proposal">
        <t>Provide a risk analysis for typical IoT environments (m2m, m2cloud) which should serve as a guidance to decide in which cases the risk is acceptable.</t>
        <t>Describe the RFC6066 <xref target="RFC6066"/> extension that allows this functionality to be used by willing clients and servers.</t>
        <t>Describe the fallback to normal operations in case server denies its consent to use the extension.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
--> 
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We would like to thank Stephen Farrell for suggesting the use of hash chains to implement a privacy-friendly connection id.</t>
    </section>
    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ...
    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo is likely to include a bunch of requests to IANA.</t>
    </section>
--> 
    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document suggests various extensions to DTLS/TLS and each of them comes with their own security and privacy considerations. Since this version of the document only suggests strawman proposals further discussions are needed to specify the details. </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
     &RFC2119;
     &RFC6347;
     &RFC6066;
     &I-D.ietf-tls-tls13;
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
<!--  &RFC7252; -->
     &I-D.ietf-dice-profile;
     &I-D.barrett-mobile-dtls;

     <reference anchor="Seggelmann">
      <front>
        <title>DTLS Mobility</title>
        <author initials="R.S." surname="Seggelmann">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="M.T." surname="Tuexen">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="E.R." surname="Rathgeb">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <date year="2012"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="ICDCN" value="12" />
    </reference>

<!-- 
    <reference anchor="Bhargavan" target="https://www.internetsociety.org/sites/default/files/T4-ProScript.pdf">
      <front>
        <title>ProScript-TLS: Verifiable Models and Systematic Testing for TLS 1.3</title>
        <author initials="K.B." surname="Bhargavan">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="N.K." surname="Kobeissi">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="B.B." surname="Beurdouche">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <date year="2016"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="TRON" value="workshop" />
    </reference>
--> 
    <reference anchor="Lamport">
      <front>
        <title>Password Authentication with Insecure Communication</title>
        <author initials="L.L." surname="Lamport">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <date year="1981"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="Commun." value="ACM" />
    </reference>

<!-- 
    <reference anchor="OMA-LWM2M" target="http://technical.openmobilealliance.org/Technical/Release_Program/docs/LightweightM2M/V1_0-20160407-C/OMA-TS-LightweightM2M-V1_0-20160407-C.pdf">
      <front>
        <title>Lightweight Machine to Machine Technical Specification</title>
        <author>
          <organization>Open Mobile Alliance</organization>
        </author>
        <date year="2016"/>
      </front>
    </reference>
--> 
   </references>
    <!-- Change Log
v00 2016-06-15  TF   Initial version
    -->
  </back>
</rfc>
